Apiculture (beekeeping) collection
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
- Government publications, reports, correspondence, 1915 - 1997; F-110-3; 67 cm of textual records 2 photographs
  - British Columbia - correspondence, 1958 - 1983; F-110-3-2; 8 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises inward and outward correspondence by various government employees, including Harvey Boone (Apiary Inspector), John Corner (Provincial Apiarist), Doug McCutcheon (Apiary Specialist), and others, on various issues affecting BC apiculture and inspections. Records include correspondence, reports, and supporting documentation.
    Boone, Harvey; McCutcheon, Doug; Textual records
    - Correspondence and reports - Harvey Boone, BC Apiary Inspector, 1958 - 1966; F-110-3-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 110-12)
    - Correspondence - Harvey Boone, BC Apiary Inspector, 1962 - 1967; F-110-3-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 110-12)
    - Correspondence and reports - Harvey Boone, BC Apiary Inspector, 1964 - 1966; F-110-3-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 110-12)
    - Correspondence - Harvey Boone, BC Apiary Inspector, 1967; F-110-3-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 110-12)
    - British Columbia Department of Agriculture, Apiary branch - correspondence, 1967 - 1971; F-110-3-2-0-5; F-110-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 110-6)
    - Correspondence and documentation on Cyanogas situation and pesticide application - Doug McCutcheon, Apiary Specialist, 1975 - 1983; F-110-3-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 110-12)
    - Correspondence and documentation on mites, pests, and diseases affecting the honeybee, 1978 - 1983; F-110-3-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 110-12)
  - British Columbia - newsletters, 1948 - 1988; F-110-3-3; 17 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises newsletters issued by the Apiary branch of the BC Department of Agriculture and later the BC Ministry of Agriculture. Records include Bee-Wise: Timely Hints on Beekeeping, the Apiary Branch Newsletter, and the Apiculture Newsletter.
    - Department of Agriculture, Apiary branch - Bee-Wise: Timely Hints on Beekeeping, 1948 - 1951; F-110-3-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 110-12)
    - Department of Agriculture, Apiary branch - Bee-Wise: Timely Hints on Beekeeping and Bee-Ginners Page, 1951 - 1963; F-110-3-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 110-12)
    - British Columbia Department of Agriculture, Apiary branch - Bee Wise - Timely Hints on Beekeeping, 1951 - 1964; F-110-3-3-0-3; F-110-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 110-6)
    - Department of Agriculture, Apiary branch - Bee-Wise: Timely Hints on Beekeeping, 1956 - 1960; F-110-3-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 110-13)
    - Department of Agriculture, Apiary branch - Bee-Wise: Timely Hints on Beekeeping, 1961 - 1971; F-110-3-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 110-13)
    - British Columbia Department of Agriculture, Apiary branch - Bee Wise - Timely Hints on Beekeeping, 1965 - 1971; F-110-3-3-0-6; F-110-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 110-6)
    - Department of Agriculture - Apiary Branch Newsletter, 1975 - 1978; F-110-3-3-0-7 (Archival box - standard 110-13)
    - Ministry of Agriculture and Food, Apiary Branch - Apiary Newsletter, 1978 - 1984; F-110-3-3-0-8 (Archival box - standard 110-13)
    - Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries - Apiculture Newsletter, 1985 - 1986; F-110-3-3-0-9 (Archival box - standard 110-13)
    - Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries - Apiculture Newsletter, 1986 - 1988; F-110-3-3-0-10 (Archival box - standard 110-13)
  - British Columbia - publications, legislation, and forms, 1925 - 1975, 1986; F-110-3-4; 6 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises publications, legislation, and forms issued or used by the BC Department of Agriculture and later by the BC Ministry of Agriculture, pertaining to apiculture-related topics and issues. Records include bulletins, circulars, pamphlets, publications, legislation, and blank forms.
    British Columbia. Department of Agriculture; Textual records
    - British Columbia Department of Agriculture - publications, 1925 - 1964; F-110-3-4-0-1; F-110-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 110-6)
    - Department of Agriculture - Bulletin No. 92: Bee Culture in British Columbia, 1928, 1948; F-110-3-4-0-2 (Archival box - standard 110-14)
    - Blank forms: Application for Registration of an Apiary, Owner's Agreement to Treat Infected Apiary, and Treatment Record, [after 1948] - [before 1969]; F-110-3-4-0-3 (Archival box - standard 110-14)
    - Department or Ministry of Agriculture - various apiary circulars, publications, and pamphlets, [ca. 1954] - 1975, 1986; F-110-3-4-0-4 (Archival box - standard 110-14)
    - Acts: Fruit, Vegetables, and Honey Grades Act: Regulations Governing Honey; Apiaries Act, 1952 - 1960; F-110-3-4-0-5; The verso of Fruit, Vegetables, and Honey Grades Act: Regulations Governing Honey document includes an annotation in pencil that appears to be a recipe for mead. The name "D.H. Pratt, Maplewood P.O., BC" is also noted, along with "Copy to Howie Morgan." (Archival box - standard 110-14)
  - British Columbia - reports, 1919, 1949 - 1997; F-110-3-5; 20 cm of textual records 2 photographs
    Sub-series comprises reports issued by the Apiary or Apiculture branches of the BC Department or Ministry of Agriculture, including annual reports by the Provincial Apiarist. Of particular note is a 1919 report to the BC Deputy Minister of Agriculture on bee inspection work, which includes photographs and drawings. Records include original reports and copies.
    McCutcheon, Doug; Jung, Ilya; British Columbia. Department of Agriculture; Textual records
    - British Columbia Department of Agriculture - report: Bee inspection work, 1919; F-110-3-5-0-1; F-110-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 110-6)
    - British Columbia Department of Agriculture - report: Bee inspection work: "Foul Brood As Seen by the Ordinary Beekeeper" (drawing), 1919; F-110-3-5-0-2; F-110-3-0-0-2
    - Copies of Department of Agriculture - Reports of Apiary Branch, 1949 - 1967; F-110-3-5-0-3 (Archival box - standard 110-14)
    - Department or Ministry of Agriculture - reports on various topics concerning apiculture, 1966 - 1967, [after 1985] - 1997; F-110-3-5-0-4; The verso of Fruit, Vegetables, and Honey Grades Act: Regulations Governing Honey document includes an annotation in pencil that appears to be a recipe for mead. The name "D.H. Pratt, Maplewood P.O., BC" is also noted, along with "Copy to Howie Morgan." (Archival box - standard 110-14)
    - Department of Agriculture - Annual Reports: Apiary Branch, 1972 - 1975; F-110-3-5-0-5 (Archival box - standard 110-14)
      Contents of file are photocopies.
    - Ministry of Agriculture - Annual Reports: Apiculture Branch, 1976 - 1979; F-110-3-5-0-6 (Archival box - standard 110-14)
    - Apiary Inspector's Annual Report by Ilya Jung, Dawson Creek, BC, 1977; F-110-3-5-0-7 (Archival box - standard 110-14)
    - Ministry of Agriculture and Food - Annual Reports: Apiculture Branch, 1980 - 1983; F-110-3-5-0-8 (Archival box - standard 110-14)
    - Apiary Specialist Annual Report - Doug McCutcheon (Lower Mainland and Vancouver Island), 1981 - 1982; F-110-3-5-0-9 (Archival box - standard 110-15)
    - Ministry of Agriculture and Food - Annual Reports: Apiculture Program, 1984 - 1985; F-110-3-5-0-10 (Archival box - standard 110-15)
    - Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries - Annual Report: Field and Special Crops Branch, 1986; F-110-3-5-0-11 (Archival box - standard 110-15)
    - Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries - Annual Reports: Apiculture Program, 1986 - 1988; F-110-3-5-0-12 (Archival box - standard 110-15)
    - Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries - Annual Report: Apiculture Program, 1989; F-110-3-5-0-13 (Archival box - standard 110-15)
  - Other governments, 1915 - 1979; F-110-3-6; 5 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises records generated by government departments and programs responsible for apiculture in their jurisdiction, other than British Columbia. Government departments represented include the Departments of Agriculture for Canada, Ontario, and the United States. Records include publications and reports.
    British Columbia. Department of Agriculture; Ontario. Department of Agriculture; United States. Department of Agriculture; Canada. Department of Agriculture; Textual records
    - Dominion of Canada Department of Agriculture, Bee Division - Exhibition Circular No. 18: Bee-Keeping in Canada (F.W.L. Sladen), 1915; F-110-3-6-0-1 (Archival box - standard 110-15)
    - Canada Department of Agriculture, 1929 - 1972; F-110-3-6-0-2; F-110-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 110-6)
    - Ontario Department of Agriculture, 1955 - 1957; F-110-3-6-0-3; F-110-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 110-6)
    - United States Department of Agriculture, 1919 - 1979; F-110-3-6-0-4; F-110-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 110-6)
- Papers, publications, reports, 1907 - [200-]; F-110-5; 9 cm of textual records
  Series comprises miscellaneous publications relating to apiculture. Documents include booklets (including The Honey Flow, published in 1907), pamphlets, articles, reports, scholarly publications, bulletins, and catalogues.
  The arrangement was provided by the archivist. Files are arranged chronologically.
  - Miscellaneous publications, F-110-5-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 110-7)
  - Miscellaneous publications, 1907 - 1957; F-110-5-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 110-7)
  - Catalogues, 1963 - 1968; F-110-5-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 110-7)
  - Miscellaneous publications, 1967 - 1971; F-110-5-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 110-7)
  - List of British Columbia Flora and Fauna Furnishing both Nectar and Pollen - compiled by John Davidson, UBC Botany, [195-?]; F-110-5-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 110-16)
    Davidson, John; Textual records
  - Poem: The Dream of a Bee Keeper by V.K. Soharev, 1953; F-110-5-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 110-16)
    Soharev, V.K.; Textual records
  - Miscellaneous beekeeping supply catalogues, [196-] - 1976; F-110-5-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 110-16)
  - Posterboard: "I Love My Bee Cee Honey", [198-?]; F-110-5-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 110-16)
  - Miscellaneous apiculture publications by Doug McCutcheon, [198-] - 2001; F-110-5-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 110-16)
    McCutcheon, Doug; Textual records
  - Report: Assessment of a Proposed Amendment to..., 1993; F-110-5-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 110-16)
    Switzer, C.M.; Hergert, Gary B.; Textual records
  - Pamphlets: The Bee Trust; Pure Honey 100% Canadian, [200-]; F-110-5-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 110-16)
- Photographs, [after 1898] - 1982, 1992; F-110-6; 13 cm of textual records 85 photographs
  Series comprises photographs primarily featuring BC beekeeping yards, personalities, exhibits, association meetings, and equipment, but also portrait photographs of former Dominion Apiarists Dr. T. Gochnaur, C. B. Gooderham, and F.W.L. Sladen.
  The arrangement was provided by the archivist. Files F-110-6-0-0-1 through F-110-6-0-0-3 are arranged alphabetically. Files F-110-6-0-0-4 through F-110-6-0-0-7 are an accrual and are arranged chronologically.
  Gooderham, C.B.; Gochnaur, T.; Boone, Harvey; Hodgson, Percy; Wilkinson, George; Sladen, F.W.L.; Beekeepers Association of British Columbia; Pearcey, G. Fred; Turnbull, W.H.; Connor, C.F.; Corner, John; Sheppard, W.J.; Finlay, A.W.; Harris, W.; Keir, Alex; Todd, F. Dundas
  - C.B. Gooderham, Dominion Apiarist, F-110-6-0-0-1; 1 photograph (Archival box - standard 110-9)
    The portrait photograph remains in its original wooden frame.
  - Dr. T. Gochnaur, Dominion Apiarist, F-110-6-0-0-2; 1 photograph (Archival box - standard 110-9)
  - "Old Photos. Honey Exhibits", 1939; F-110-6-0-0-3; 15 photographs (Archival box - standard 110-9)
    Two of the exhibit photographs are labelled "Honey section. Vancouver Exhibit, 1939"; the remainder are undated and unannotated. Exhibit photographs have been removed from original cardboard frames, and any studio information contained on the original frame has been annotated on to slipcovers.
  - Miscellaneous photographs of BC beekeeping yards, personalities, exhibits, association meetings, and equipment, [after 1898], 1920 - [after 1924], 1941 - 1982, 1992; F-110-6-0-0-4; 63 photographs (Archival box - standard 110-16)
    File consists of 63 black and white, colour, and sepia tone photographs. The majority are original, but there are some copies. Most include annotations identifying content and dates. Personalities pictured include G. Fred Pearcey, W.H. Turnbull, C.F. Connor, Percy Hodgson, John Corner, among others. Locations featured include Armstrong, Creston, Kelowna, and Vernon. There are a number of images featuring honey exhibits from around the province. Of particular note is an original photograph from after 1924 that features W.J. Sheppard, A.W. Finlay, W. Harris, W.H. Turnbull, Alex Keir and F. Dundas Todd, all of whom worked for the BC Department of Agriculture.
    Photographic materials
  - F.W.L. Sladen, first Dominion Apiarist, Ottawa, [191-]; F-110-6-0-0-5; 1 photograph (Archival box - standard 110-16)
    The print appears to be a copy. It has been removed from its original wooden frame, and the frame disposed of. The same annotation that was on the verso of the frame appears on the verso of the print.
  - Beekeepers' Association of B.C. exhibit, [192-?]; F-110-6-0-0-6; 1 photograph (Archival box - standard 110-16)
    The image is affixed to a mat board.
  - Miscellaneous photographs of Harvey Boone, Percy Hodgson, and George Wilkinson, [195-]; F-110-6-0-0-7; 3 photographs (Archival box - standard 110-16)
    The prints of Boone and Wilkinson appear to be copies, while the Hodgson photograph is a print from the UBC Department of Extension.
- Subject files, 1918 - 1999; F-110-7; 12 cm of textual records 32 photographs
  Series comprises records created or collected by various individuals involved in the BC beekeeping field on a variety of apiculture-related topics and activities. Records consist of correspondence, newspaper clippings, publications, catalogues, a bound volume of clippings, and an original manuscript that includes photographs.
  9 photographs located in F-110-7-0-0-1
  23 photographs located in F-110-7-0-0-4
  - Bound volume: Newspaper clippings of early British Columbia beekeeping history (John Corner collector), 1918 - 1982, 1999; F-110-7-0-0-1 (Newspaper box 110-17)
    File represents a bound volume of newspaper clippings pertaining primarily to BC beekeeping history, but also to apiculture-related issues in general. Clippings are mainly from BC newspapers, but there are also some from other provinces and international sources. Leaves of the volume are labelled chronologically by year, but the 1940s and 1950s are grouped together. Clippings through the 1970s are sporadic. Up to the 1940s, newspaper clippings are affixed to the leaves with tape or adhesive. Thereafter, clippings are held loosely between the leaves and additional materials have been added including some correspondence, photographs, and pamphlets.
    Corner, John; Textual records; Photographic materials
    There are 9 loose colour photographs located in the 1970 section.
  - Miscellaneous research material pertaining to the history of beekeeping in BC (John Boone collector), 1925 - 1947, 1959 - 1979, 1989 - 1995; F-110-7-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 110-16)
    File consists of miscellaneous materials related to the history of beekeeping in BC collected by John Boone. Records include original beekeeping permits (for H.J. Minall and H.R. Bryett), pamphlets, catalogues, original correspondence to H.J. Minall, Apiary Branch annual reports, handwritten recollections by John Stawn (Vernon and Peace River areas), recollections by John Corner on post war beekeeping in BC, a BC Honey Producers Association brochure, beekeeping booklets from Alex Sacharoff (Terrace, BC) printed in Russian, and a booklet of transparencies featuring the anatomy of the honeybee.
    Boone, John; Stawn, John; Corner, John; Minall, H.J.; Bryett, H.R.; Textual records
  - A.E. Pittaway and W.H. Turnbull correspondence on BC apiarian history, [after 1945] - 1955; F-110-7-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 110-16)
    Pittaway, A.E.; Turnbull, W.H.; Textual records
  - Manuscript: Brief from (or outline) - History of Beekeeping of British Columbia, 1914 to 1950 (V.K. Soharev, Apiarist, Nelson, BC), [ca. 1947 - 1957]; F-110-7-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 110-16)
    Soharev, V.K.; Textual records; Photographic materials
    There are 21 original black and white and sepia tone photographs and newspaper clippings affixed to pages of this bound manuscript. There are 2 additional loose photographs (one of which is mounted on cardboard), a letter, and a listing of publications interleaved between the pages. Three pages have come loose from the binding of the manuscript.
  - Copies of miscellaneous clippings, reports, and other documentation on the Peace River area (Doug McCutcheon collector), 1958 - 1972; F-110-7-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 110-16)
    McCutcheon, Doug; Textual records; Peace River
  - Personal correspondence regarding sale of pollen - Harvey Boone, 1964 - 1966; F-110-7-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 110-16)
    Boone, Harvey; Textual records
  - Correspondence and other documentation regarding the establishment of the Winson Library, UBC, 1965 - 1969; F-110-7-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 110-16)
    File includes 2 photographs.
- Moving images, [196-?] - 1977; F-110-8; 7 film reels
  Series comprises films featuring a variety of apiculture-related topics.
  The arrangement was provided by the archivist.
  Moving images
  - Honey Extracting - Processing, [196-?]; F-110-8-0-0-0-1 (Film reel: 16mm OBJ-4624)
    Item is a silent, colour film featuring the processing of honey from its transport by truck to the Bee Cee Honey plant through to canning and labelling by factory workers on assembly lines. School children and girl guides are shown entering the plant for tours. The Bee Cee Honey plant building includes a "Hodgson's Bee Supplies Ltd." sign suggesting it may have been filmed in New Westminster, BC, where Hodgson's was based at the time. One of the transport trucks shown in the film bears the slogan, "Another Load of Silverbow Honey." Silverbow is a Washington state-based honey company.
    Tail leader includes the following annotation: "Canyon + Penticton + Hope. The End." The film was originally on a metal reel, from which it has been removed and wound onto a 3mm core. The original metal reel was annotated as follows: "Honey Extraction - Processing. Return to Apiary Branch. Dept. of Agriculture. Courthouse. Vernon BC V1T 4W5." There are no beginning or end credits.
  - Secret in the Hive, [196-]; F-110-8-0-0-0-2; F-110-7-0-0-0-1; Badly scratched, heavily tinted a rose colour. Illustrates the life of the queen. Bees' behaviour patterns including dances and colour/pattern recognition. (Film reel: 16mm OBJ-2157)
  - Honey, [197-]; F-110-8-0-0-0-3; F-110-7-0-0-0-2; Reel it is stored on has too small of a center hole to fit on winders. Single shrinkage gauge measurement taken. Only first few feet viewed. Film begins with a newly married couple walking out of a church. Colour is rose-tinted and appears very faded. May not belong with apiculture films - though was stored with them on shelves. (Film reel: 16mm OBJ-2158)
  - Pests of the Apiary (and Diseases), 1977; F-110-8-0-0-0-4; F-110-7-0-0-0-3; Hole in centre of reel too small to fit on winder. Single shrinkage gauge measurement. Quality of picture and colour is still good. (Film reel: 16mm OBJ-2159)
  - Bees, 1977; F-110-8-0-0-0-5; F-110-7-0-0-0-4; Sprocket holes too small to fit on Moviscop or on the shrinkage gauge. 8mm film. (Film reel: 8mm OBJ-2160)
  - Language of the Bee: A Case History of the Scientific Method, 1965; F-110-8-0-0-0-6; F-110-7-0-0-0-5; Sprocket holes too badly damaged to take measurement at start of film. Rose tinted and badly faded. Mix of animation and live action. (Film reel: 16mm OBJ-2161)
    Moody Institute of Science
  - Biography of a Bee, 1965; F-110-8-0-0-0-7; F-110-7-0-0-0-6; Several sections from beginning and end of film not attached - torn off. Sprocket holes too damaged for shrinkage gauge reading near the beginning of the film. Mix of live action and illustrations. Very bad condition. Sprocket holes torn. Emulsion layer peeling in some areas. (Film reel: 16mm OBJ-2162)